Finding Aid for Counseling Services (University of Michigan) Records 1956-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Counseling Services (University of Michigan) Records 1956-1990, 1968-1976
University of Michigan. Counseling Services.
4.5 linear feet
Unit established within the office of the Vice-President for Student Affairs of the University of Michigan as counseling information clearinghouse which later accepted responsibility for counseling in areas of student mental health problems, problem pregnancy, marital relations, human sexuality, and racial and minority affairs. Records include minutes from various committees within Counseling Services; topical files; reports put out by Counseling Services; and printed materials.
93849 Bimu 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (Donor 8128 ) was received beginning in 1993. Periodic accessions to continue.
The records are open for research.
The origins of Counseling Services are found in the 1961 merger of the responsibilities of the Dean of Men and the Dean of Women into the new Office of Student Affairs, under the Office of the Vice President for Student Affairs. At that time a new position, Coordinator of Counseling, was created; the Coordinator also served as the Executive Secretary of the University Committee on Student Counseling Services. The Office of the Coordinator of Counseling assisted students in obtaining non-academic information and oversaw the release of student information to non-university agencies. The University Committee on Student Counseling Services began publishing the Faculty and Staff Guide to Counseling and Student Services in 1964 in conjunction with the administration to the Michigan Union. This publication, which continued until 1977, described all of the non-academic services on campus that were available to students. The function of the office of the Coordinator of Counseling was characterized in the Guide as "the chief clearinghouse of counseling information, not a clinical agency." [1969/70 Guide to Counseling and Student Services, p. 16]
During the 1965/66 academic year, the office of the Vice President for Student Affairs was reorganized. A Student Affairs Counseling Office (SACO) was created in 1967, incorporating the Counseling Division of the Bureau of Psychological Services. Edward S. Bordin, chief of Counseling Division, was named Director of the Counseling Office and remained so through 1973. Elizabeth Davenport served as assistant director from 1965 until 1969/70.
The Office of the Vice President for Student Affairs underwent yet another reorganization during the academic year 1970/71. The Counseling Office became Counseling Services. Its responsibility was to coordinate all counseling within the Office of Student Services: direct counseling services, consultation to university faculty and staff, educational programming, and research into and coordination of community mental health campus-wide. The most significant development to take place was the addition of the Counseling, Referral and Information Service (76 Guide), a 24 hour/7 day-a-week telephone hotline, devoted to counseling, problem solving, and referral.
During the early 1970s, minority counseling, which included Black Information Counseling (BIC), was added to direct counseling services. Consultation services expanded to include consultation within the housing office and the Peer Counselor Program. The Educational Programming and Consultation (EPC) program included teaching services in the Psychology Department, graduate intern training, sex education, and the Drug Education Project. Individual counseling services to students continued to be offered in conjunction with the Mental Health Clinic at University Health Services and the Bureau of Psychological Services.
During the 1974/75 academic year Counseling Services merged with the Mental Health Clinic of University Health Services. The two together retained the name of Counseling Services. As a result, major emphasis was put on counseling individuals, couples, and groups in addition to counseling in the areas of minority concerns, problem pregnancy, marital relations, and human sexuality. It is interesting to note that the Guide still listed the main function of Counseling Services as a clearinghouse of information. A major focus of the 1978/79 academic year was the implementation of daily professional staff teams to provide students with immediate walk-in service.
In the 1980s, Counseling Services added the Human Sexuality Office and the Sexual Assault Crisis Center. Increasing support was given to these two areas until 1990 when each became a separate unit under the Vice President for Student Affairs. As demands for counseling continued to increase, more emphasis was placed on direct, one-on-one and group counseling. In order to document the numbers of individuals using counseling services, a data management system was set up in 1982/83 to provide complete and updated information on services delivered.
Currently, Counseling Services focuses on helping students resolve personal difficulties and acquiring the skills, attitudes, abilities, and knowledge that will enable them to take full advantage of their college experience. Services include individual, group, and marital counseling, consultation to university units, the 76-Guide telephone hotline, as well as workshops dealing with such topics as assertiveness, stress, and eating disorders. Also available are assistance programs for alcohol-related problems and self-help groups.
Directors of the Counseling Service
Co-ordinator of Counseling
1962-1963 Mark G. Noffsinger
1963-1965 Elizabeth Davenport (Assistant Director)
Counseling Office Director
1965-1967 Elizabeth Davenport
1967-1970 Ed Bordin
Counseling Services Director
1971-1973 Ed Bordin
1973-1977 Donna Nagely
1978-1990 Harold Korn
1990-1991 James P. Whiteside (Acting Director)
1991- Annie Delories Sloan
The records of Counseling Services provide a unique look at the response of the university to the non-academic needs of the student body. The records span the years 1956-1992; the bulk of the materials covers 1968-1976. The records are divided into four series: Minutes; Topical Files; Reports; and Printed Works.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Counseling Services.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan--Students--Mental health services.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Student Affairs.
Genre/Form:
College publications.
- Minutes
  The Minutes Series (1.25 linear feet) consists of minutes from the various committees related to Counseling Services. The Staff Meeting minutes and the Coordinating Council minutes provide the best documentation of the overall scope of the Counseling Services office. Within the weekly minutes of these two committees, the researcher will find reports of the various programs and committees operating within the Counseling Office. The minutes of the Advisory and Policy of Care Committees illustrate the various ethical and operational questions confronting the staff in their attempt to meet the needs of the ever-changing student body. Lastly, the minutes of the University Committee on Student Counseling Services document the earliest years of counseling, the Office of the Coordinator of Counseling.
  - Advisory Committee
    - 1966-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Committee to Study Counseling Services 1956 (Box 1)
  - Coordinating Council 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Counseling Committee 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Counseling Review Committee 1983 (Box 1)
  - Educational Programming and Consultation Committee
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Mental Health Staff 1967-1972 (Box 1)
  - Merit Committee 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Minority Counseling and Information (MCI) 1976 (Box 1)
  - Needs Assessment Committee 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Peer Program Development Team 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Peer Programming Team (PPT) 1977 (Box 1)
  - Policy of Care Committee (POC)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1990 (Box 1)
  - Professional Education Committee (PEC) 1981-1987 (Box 1)
  - 76 Guide Committee 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Staff Meetings
    - 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1973 (Box 2)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - 1985-1987 (Box 2)
    - 1987-1991 (Box 2)
  - Steering Committee 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Unit Committee 1971-1977 (Box 2)
  - University Committee on Student Counseling Services 1964-1965 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files (2.0 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically and document the various services and programs available to students. The overall functions of Counseling Services are best described within the "General," Goal Statements," and "Objectives" folders. The "Annual Report Background Files" contain the reports submitted from various programs within Counseling that were used in the preparation of the Annual Report to the President.
  The "Student Survey on Counseling" files include the 1956 survey conducted by the Counseling Study Committee of the University of Michigan. The survey was conducted to examine student attitudes about the available counseling services on campus. As a result of this survey the 1958 publication, A Guide to the Resources for Student Counseling and Advising at the University of Michigan was created. This publication is the predecessor of the Guide to Counseling, published by Counseling Services in the 1960s and 1970s. In addition to the Guide, a statement of goals was written for a university-wide counseling program. The Counseling Services Office was an outgrowth of this goal statement.
  The records in this series also document programs created to meet the needs of the student body. The 76-Guide files give evidence of the 24-hour referral and information service sponsored by Counseling Office that started as an experiment in the lobby of the Student Activities Building. This unique counseling service, which is still ongoing, provides immediate counseling and referral.
  The Educational Programming and Consultation Unit files relate this out-reach branch of counseling, which is responsible for creating and implementing programs to assist other university units. The researcher will find proposals, program modules and written objectives within the EP&C files. Additionally, there is information on two of the most popular programs: the Housing Consultation project, a program to support residence hall staff in their work with students; and the Peer Development program, a program allowing trained students to counsel their peers.
  - General 1964-1977 (Box 2)
  - Academic Counseling 1971-1974 (Box 2)
  - Activities Reports 1970 (Box 2)
  - Advertisements 1979-1983 (Box 2)
  - Alcohol Abuse Prevention Committee 1977 (Box 2)
  - All Day Workshops 1978-1983 (Box 2)
  - Alternatives for University Involvement in Child Care 1972 (proposal) (Box 2)
  - Annual Report Background Files
    - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Assertion Training Workshop 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Athletic Counselor 1974 (Box 2)
  - Budget Materials
    - 1966-1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Career Counseling 1968 (Box 2)
  - Community Counseling Services Survey 1964 (Box 2)
  - Compensatory Education 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Coordination of Counseling Committee 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Counseling Centers Annual Data Bank Survey 1983 (Box 2)
  - Counseling Statistics (number of students seen)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Counselor Education 1972 (Box 2)
  - Counselor on Duty (COD) 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Direct Services 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Disabled Students 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Drug Education Committee 1968-1971 (Box 2)
  - Drug Education Project 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Drug Help 1970 (Box 2)
  - Educational Programming and Consultation Unit (EP&C)
    - General 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Housing Consultation 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Peer Program Development Team 1976 (Box 3)
      (includes minutes)
  - Family Advocate 1972 (Box 3)
  - Field Placement Committee
    - 1969-1972 (Box 3)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 3)
    - 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - Focus Group Program 1972-1975 (Box 3)
  - Goal Statements 1973-1977 (Box 3)
  - Group Therapy Program 1975 (Box 3)
  - Homosexuality 1970-1976 (Box 3)
  - In-Service Training 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Internships and Field Placements 1973-1980 (Box 3)
  - Issues in Counseling and Consultation with Students 1969-1970 (Psychology 502) (Box 3)
  - Law School Consultation 1974-1976 (Box 3)
  - Library Listings 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Mental Health Clinic
    - General 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Merger 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Monthly Reports 1968-1974 (Box 3)
    - Six Month Progress Reports 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - Minority Counseling and Information (MCI) 1970-1979 (Box 3)
  - Objectives 1974-1979 (Box 3)
  - Ongoing Orientation for New Students 1977 (Course Proposal) (Box 3)
  - Organizational Development Network 1970
    - Paper, "The Development of Consulting Relationships," 1973 (Box 3)
  - Parent Orientation 1975 (Box 3)
  - Peer Counseling 1978 (Psychology 304-307) (Box 3)
  - Pilot Program 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Private Practice 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Problem Pregnancy Counseling 1971-1978 (Box 3)
  - Prom 1981 (Moments to Remember-skit) (Box 3)
  - Psychologist Registration Act 1976 (Box 3)
  - Publications 1966-1971 (Box 3)
  - Reorganization 1971 (Box 3)
  - Research 1967 (Box 3)
  - Resource Allocation Committee 1975 (Box 3)
  - Search Committee Guidelines 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Second Echelon Committee 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - 76 Guide
    - General 1968-1974 (Box 3)
    - Staff 1972-1983 (Box 3)
  - Sex Education
    - General 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - Committee 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Task Force 1972 (Box 3)
  - Slide Show Script undated (Box 3)
  - Social Work 1974-1975 (field placements) (Box 4)
  - Social Work Registration Act 1976 (Box 4)
  - Staff List 1971-1982 (Box 4)
  - Student Advising Program 1969 (Box 4)
  - Student Health Procedures undated (Box 4)
  - Student Needs Assessment 1974-1977 (Box 4)
  - Student Record Confidentiality 1968-1976 (Box 4)
  - Student Survey on Counseling
    - Housing Unit Reports 1957, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Organizational and Preliminary to Final Tables 1956-1957 (Box 4)
    - Tables 1957 (Box 4)
    - Tables II 1957, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Substance Use and the College Experience Project (SUCE) 1978 (Box 4)
  - Veterans 1969-1972 (Box 4)
- Reports, 9 folders
  The Reports Series (.75 linear feet), generated by the office of Counseling Services or by members of the office is arranged in alphabetical order. Topics include sex education, handicapped needs, drug education, and evaluations of counseling services.
  - Academic Anxiety Reduction Group Project Report, 1976-77 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Campus and Community Pre-Marital and Marital Counseling Services-Phases II and III, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Counseling Services Walden Woods Peer Counselor Training Weekend, September 17-19, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Entering Student's Preparation for Self-Regulation 1969 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - A Functional Review of Counseling, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - A Guide to Guide, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Handicapped Student Program 1968-1969, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Information About Drugs, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Interfaces Between a University Telephone Counseling Service Utilizing Peer Counselors and Related Campus/Community Agencies, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Levels of Concern in Problem Areas and Help Seeking of University of Michigan Students: Preliminary Findings, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Motivational Conflict and Vocational Development, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Recommendations for Sex Education at the University of Michigan, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Report of the Handicapped Student Program Committee, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Report of the Special Study Committee for the Office of Student Affairs, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Report of the University Task Force on Student Counseling, July 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Report on Issues Confronting the Student Affairs Counseling Office (SACO), 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Report on Survey of Campus Sources Available for Career Counseling and Occupational Information, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Student Affairs Counseling Office Status Report, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Student Attitudes Toward Drug Education Programs at the University of Michigan-Report of a Survey Conducted for the Drug Education Survey Sub-Committee, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Student Data Survey Summary Report, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Student Personnel Services for Veterans-Issues, Recommendations, Resources, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - A Survey of University Student to Student Counseling Programs, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Three Indices to Tests, Report on Counseling Testing at the University of Michigan, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The University 24-Hour Telephone Counseling Service: Paraprofessionals in Community Mental Health, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Printed Works (Box 5)
  The Printed Works series (.5 linear feet) is comprised of Annual Reports, Brochures, Newsletters, and Manuals.